Guide to the Pierre Van Rysselberghe Papers
Stanford University. Libraries.
Department of Special Collections and University Archives
Pierre Van Rysselberghe papers
1932-1973
SC0298
Van Rysselberghe, Pierre, 1905-
54 Linear feet
Papers include correspondence, class materials, articles and reprints, lab notes, and other materials pertaining to his research and his teaching career.
Department of Special Collections and University Archives Green Library 557 Escondido Mall Stanford, CA 94305-6064 Email: specialcollections@stanford.edu Phone: (650) 725-1022 URL: http://library.stanford.edu/spc
Administrative Information
Information about Access
This collection is open for research.
Biographical/Historical Sketch
Pierre van Rysselberghe, a chemist and chemical engineer, earned his masters (1928) and doctorate (1929) at Stanford University. He taught at the University of Oregon and at Stanford. He died in 1977.
Description of the Collection
Papers include correspondence, class materials, articles and reprints, lab notes, and other materials pertaining to his research and his teaching career.
Access Terms
Van Rysselberghe, Pierre, 1905-; Chemistry--Study and teaching.; Thermodynamics.
Collection Contents
- Papers
  - Mimeographed, mostly handwritten text ELEMENTS OF THE THERMODYNAMICS OF IRREVERSIBLE PROCESSES (Box 1)
  - Mimeographed - notes (for course or book) 3 entries (Box 1)
  - Mimeographed texts - literature and chemistry; letter 3/12/58 Abanthay to R. (Box 1)
  - Typed notes with ink additions (Box 1)
  - Mimeograph notes (Box 1)
  - Technical Report "Polerographic Study of Corrosion Phenomena: Aluminum and its Alloys." R & John McGee 1948-49 (Office of Naval Research) (Box 1)
  - Mimeographed drafts with article “Electrolytic Formation of Insulating oxide Films on Zircanium... taken from a dissertation by Grover C. Willis (Box 1)
  - Correspondence, 1935-37; “letters and documents concerning my monograph on affinity” (Box 1)
  - J. M. McGee – Navy correspondence, 1946-47 (Box 1)
  - P. Van Rysselberghe et al papers published 1942-46 (Box 1)
  - Project for Chem Edu (“Problems of Electrochemical Nomenclature with Definitions”) (Box 1)
  - Johnsen paper (include. Letter, “Herman” to Rysselberghe) (Box 1)
  - Mimeographed notes (for course) (Box 1)
  - Physical Chemistry – course given in the winter and spring quarters 1932 (Box 1)
  - Physical Chemistry Chem 440, 441, 442 (Box 1)
  - Physical Chemistry 440, 441, 442, 1949-50 (Box 1)
  - [Physical Chemistry 443 – spring 1955] (Box 1)
  - (Gibbian?) Thermodynamics in Physical Chemistry Chem. 289 (Box 1)
  - Current University Affairs (1953-54) (Box 1)
  - General Correspondence, Oct. 1950- Sept. 1953 (Box 1)
  - Abstracts and Printed matter – “CITCE” (Box 1)
  - United States Information Service (Box 1)
  - Round Table Talk, April 1952 (Box 1)
  - Abstracts of Talks and Papers on Polarography (Haly, etc.) Fulbright (Box 1)
  - Documents and correspondence concerning Fulbright bill for Haly etc. (Box 1)
  - General correspondence, to and from M. Marcel Pourbaix, Sept. 1949-Nov. 1952 (Box 1)
  - Centre Belge d’Etude de la Corosion: CEBELCOR (Box 1)
  - Electrochemistry lectures (with manuscripts of papers) and figures (Box 1)
  - Revision of paper on Potential pH diagram of halogens – for Cambridge meeting (Box 2)
  - Correspondence with publishers – Atlas, May 1948-May 1950 (Box 2)
  - Personal correspondence with M. Marcel Pourbaix, May 1949-July 1952 (Box 2)
  - Correspondence with M. Marcel Pourbaix, 1946-49 (Box 2)
  - “The Anodic Oxidation of Methanol on Single-Crystal and Polycrystalline Platinum,” dissertation by Wilson Harvey Smart, 1964 (Box 2)
  - Kraus, Charles A. (Box 2)
  - Kendall, James (Box 2)
  - Keyes, Frederick G. (Box 2)
  - Kilpatrick, Martin, Jr. (Box 2)
  - Kirkwood, J. G. (Box 2)
  - Klemensiewicz, Z. (Box 2)
  - Chimie Physique Thermodynamique Chimique par R. Defay (Box 2)
  - CITCE – 9th reunion (Box 2)
  - Leighton, Philip A. (Box 2)
  - Double Layer-Surface Conductivity - Electrokinetics (October 1933) (Box 2)
  - On Possible Evidence for an Hypothesis of Biological Coupling (paper by John Taugher) (Box 2)
  - Levine, S. (Box 2)
  - Longsworth, L. G. (Box 2)
  - Important reprints (Box 2)
  - Notes and manuscript of article (Box 2)
  - Electrolytes spring quarter 1939 (Box 2)
  - Muller, Otto H. (reprints) (Box 2)
  - R. Breuer (Box 2)
  - Outline of talk – Portland, May 18, 1950 (Box 2)
  - Notes (for course? 1944-45) (Box 2)
  - Computations concerning the thermodynamics of the Debye-Huckel theory (Oct. – Dec. 1933) (Box 2)
  - Lange-Koenig Electrochemistry of Phase Boundaries (Box 2)
  - Transport Numbers – Nutting’s work (Box 2)
  - On Acid Strength, April-May-June 1936 (Box 2)
  - Projects and manuscripts of papers on Thermodynamics (Box 2)
  - Van Rysselberghe (Thermodynamic Theory of Affinity) (Box 2)
  - Thesis presented for the degree of Master of Science, F. C. Coleman, June 1914 (Box 2)
  - Thermodynamics of the Electric Field, May – June 1936 (Box 2)
  - Double Layer (Box 2)
  - German Reprints (Box 2)
  - CITCE Report (Box 2)
  - Mail Carbons 1952 (Box 2)
  - Process Industries Picture Flow Sheets, revised edition (Box 2)
  - Correspondence 1947, J. M. McGee (Box 2)
  - Correspondence 1946- (Box 2)
  - US Navy Correspondence J. M. McGee 1949 (Box 2)
  - ONR - to #1 1949 NR-051-041 Reports (Box 2)
  - Corrosion information (Box 2)
  - J. M. McGee – US Navy 1948 (Box 2)
  - Correspondence 1949 (Box 2)
  - Correspondence 1944-46 (Box 3)
  - Correspondence and articles, Puget Sound Chemist (Box 3)
  - CITCE June 1971 (Box 3)
  - Electrochemical Concepts and Conventions, Notes (Box 3)
  - Correspondence, 1948 (Box 3)
  - Monsanto co. (Box 3)
  - Ghigi, Elisa (Box 3)
  - Gordon, A. R. (Box 3)
  - Gillis, J. (Box 3)
  - Guillissen, J. (Box 3)
  - Gross, Philipp (Box 3)
  - Guggenheim, E. A. (Box 3)
  - Gutmann, F. (Box 3)
  - Guitton, M. L. (Box 3)
  - Figures (Box 3)
  - Calore di Reazione e Temperatura by Antonio Giacalore (Box 3)
  - Gerucher, H. (Box 3)
  - Ghosh, J. C. (Box 3)
  - Vocabulaire de la Corrosion (Box 3)
  - CITCE Report (Box 3)
  - Marcel – Mail (Box 3)
  - Mail – April 1963 (Box 3)
  - Mimeographed Notes (CITCE?) in French (Box 3)
  - Technical Report #5 to the Office of Naval Research “Direct Observation and Analysis of Crack Propagation in Iron – 3% Silicon Crystals” (Box 3)
  - Notes and mimeographs (Box 3)
  - Centre Belge D’Etude de la Corrosion “Cebelcor” (Box 3)
  - Reprints/Translated articles (Box 3)
  - Chem 278 Stanford University Spring Quarter 1960: Introduction to Molecular Structure and Molecular Spectroscopy (Box 3)
  - Mechanicians’ shop and National Assoc. of Corrosion Engineers (Box 3)
  - Comminion [?] I CITCE (Box 3)
  - Dean, Robert B. (Box 3)
  - Dannay, J. D. H. (Box 3)
  - Davies, Cecil W. (Box 3)
  - Dupont, Yvonne (Box 3)
  - Du Bois, Robert (Box 3)
  - Stockholm (Box 3)
  - Correspondence and Articles reviews (Box 3)
  - Correspondence 1967 (Box 3)
  - Correspondence 1966-67 and CITCE (Box 3)
  - Correspondence and Article reviews (Box 3)
  - V. G. Levich – attempt to emigrate from USSR (Box 3)
  - Correspondence, 1966-7 (Box 3)
  - Mimeographed Notes (Box 3)
  - International Society of Electrochemistry (ISE) (formerly CITCE) (Box 4)
  - Box with notes, correspondence, review and text of “Thermodynamic Kinetics – Application to Several Electrochemical Problems” by T. Markovic (Box 4)
  - Correspondence and Article reviews (Box 4)
  - Correspondence and Article reviews (Box 4)
  - Office of Naval Research – Technical Report “Coulostatic Study of Residual Oxygen in Electrochemical Investigations” 1965 & European Scientific Notes, 1970 (Box 4)
  - NASA-Ames “Development of a CO2 – H2O Solid Oxide Electrolyte Electrolysis System” Annual Reports 1969-71 (Box 4)
  - Correspondence and Article reviews 1968 (Box 4)
  - Correspondence and Article reviews (Box 4)
  - Correspondence and Article reviews (Box 4)
  - CITCE membership 1968-69, 1973 (Box 4)
  - International Union of Pure and Applied Chemistry Information Bulletin, #27 and 28, 1966-67 (Box 4)
  - Conference and meeting info (Box 4)
  - Edited manuscript (photocopy) (Box 4)
  - ISO Recommendations (Box 4)
  - Correspondence and misc. papers (Box 4)
  - CITCE report French version (Box 4)
  - Bibliography V.R. (Box 4)
  - Lange-1964-65 (Box 4)
  - Reprints (Box 4)
  - Lange’s paper for Electrochemical Society (Box 4)
  - Mail [1959-60] (Box 4)
  - Atomic Energy Commission Progress Reports (Box 4)
  - Office of Naval Research Technical Report (Box 4)
  - Office of Naval Research (Box 4)
  - Office of Naval Research (Box 4)
  - Inorganic chemistry final exam, 3/20/57 (Box 5)
  - Corrosion Processes: the British Contribution to their Understanding (Box 5)
  - CITCE-IUPAC reports and errata, 1964 (Box 5)
  - “On the Signs of Onsager’s Reciprocity Relations in Irreversible Thermodynamics” (Box 5)
  - Correspondence, 1964 (Box 5)
  - Correspondence and Articles submitted for publication (Box 5)
  - Correspondence and Articles (Box 5)
  - Office of Naval Research, Technical Report, “Thermodynamic Properties of the Electrical Double Layer” (Box 5)
  - CITCE 1956-64 (Box 5)
  - XIV CITCE Mockba 1963 (Box 5)
  - Stainless steel (ESFC) reactions by polarograph (Box 5)
  - Graphs (Box 5)
  - “Le Concept de Temps dans le Principe d’Onsager” by Satosi Watanabe (Box 5)
  - “Elements de Chimie Physique” by R. Defay (Box 5)
  - “Academy of sciences of the USSR – Reports of the 4th Soviet Conference on Electrochemistry” 1956 (Box 5)
  - Bulletin of the Atomic Scientist Apr. 1966 (Box 5)
  - “Chimie Physique Thermodynamique Chimique” by R. Defay (Box 5)
  - Correspondence, notes, articles (Box 5)
  - Timmermans, J. (Box 5)
  - Lecat, Maurice (Box 5)
  - Latimer, W. M. (Box 5)
  - LaMer, Victor K. (Box 5)
  - Kunz, H. H. (Box 5)
  - Huttig, Gustav F. (Box 5)
  - Hoffman, Hugh M. (Box 5)
  - Thermod. – Wattens (Box 5)
  - Electrode Kinetics – Linear (Box 5)
  - CITCE (Box 5)
  - Reprints (Box 6)
  - Notecards (Box 7)
  - CITCE 1962 (Box 8)
  - Coupling of Chemical Reactions (including correspondence with Li) (Box 8)
  - Horiuti, Juro (Box 8)
  - Homes, Georges (Box 8)
  - Navy Project 1947, 1948 P. Delahay (Box 8)
  - Thermodynamics of Irreversible Processes (lecture course, Winter-Spring 1958-9) (Box 8)
  - “The Electrolytic Reduction of Carbon Dioxide of Mercury Cathodes by Truman Eldridge Tester” (Ph.D. thesis for Univ. of Oregon, 1964) (Box 8)
  - Russian Vocabulary (Box 8)
  - Russian Notebook (Box 8)
  - [Lab notebook – inside front cover “Nick Stolica MC Clue 5”] (Box 8)
  - John M. McGee, Lab Notes 1948, no. IV of corrosion series of notes (Box 8)
  - John M. McGee, Lab Notes 1949 (Box 8)
  - Pierre papers (Box 8)
  - Publications – list, etc. (Box 8)
  - Gehenian, J. (Box 8)
  - Gauguin, R. (Box 8)
  - “Current Efficiencies in the Anodic Polishing of Metals” (Master’s thesis for Univ. of Oregon, 1956) (Box 8)
  - Amount of Substance (Box 8)
  - Octahedran paper (Box 8)
  - L12 D12 (Box 8)
  - MD Kinetics (Box 9)
  - Valensi (Box 9)
  - dv1/dA2 = dV2/dA1 (Box 9)
  - IUPAC – CITCE (Box 9)
  - Corrosion paper (Box 9)
  - CITCE – Strasbourg Sept. 1969 (Box 9)
  - CITCE – Administration (Box 9)
  - Log-book of polarogams, started December 27, 1944 I (Box 9)
  - Log-book of polarogams, started January 26, 1945 II (Box 9)
  - Log-book of polarogams, started Feb. 9, 1945 IV (Box 9)
  - Log-book of polarogams, started July 5, 1945 V (Box 9)
  - Log-book of polarogams, started July 13, 1945 VI (Box 9)
  - Log-book of polarogams, started July 27, 1945 VII (Box 9)
  - Log-book of polarogams, started Oct. 10, 1945, ended Nov. 12, 1945 VIII (Box 9)
  - Log-book of polarogams, started Nov. 13, 1945, ended Dec. 12, 1945 IX (Box 9)
  - Log-book of polarogams, started Dec. 12, 1945 X (Box 9)
  - Log-book of polarogams, started Jan. 19, 1946 XI (Box 9)
  - Corrosion Phenomena Task #1 started Oct. 20, 1946 (Box 9)
  - Corrosion Research U. S. Navy Project (Box 9)
  - Report to Graduate Council on Matter of Ph.D. degree (VR’s list of publications, see also under P in general mail) (Box 9)
  - Graduate students (Box 9)
  - Graduate matters (1947-48) (Box 9)
  - I. O2 Polarograph Curves Corrosion Phenomena, Jan.-Feb. 1947 (Box 9)
  - II. O2 Polarograms 1947 (Box 9)
  - Using old E.M.F. set up Old O2 and CO2 curves (Box 9)
  - I. CO2 polarograms 1946-47 Dec. 1946-Jan-Feb. 1947 (Box 9)
  - History of “Affinity” (Box 9)
  - The Beginnings of Modern Science (Philosophy 341) Lectures on Lavoisier (Box 9)
  - Library Committee and other Committee matters (Box 9)
  - CO2 Curves III Apr.-May-June 1947 (Box 9)
  - Scientia and lecture at Sanita, Rome (Box 9)
  - Van Rysselberghe LA talk (Box 9)
  - Articles to be examined (Box 9)
  - Mr. Hewes’s notes on Gibbs’ lectures (Box 9)
  - Rapport CITCE (Box 9)
  - War Assets Committee (Box 9)
  - Library (Box 9)
  - Navy Report (Box 9)
  - Percarbonate paper J. Phys. Chem. Coll. Chem (Box 9)
  - Physical and Inorganic Division of A.C.S. (Box 9)
  - Requisitions (copies), Requests for purchases, etc. (Box 9)
  - Schedule, student matters (Box 9)
  - CO2 electrode (Reiner, Richard Carl) (Box 9)
  - Diffusion, notes on diffusion and irreversible phenomena (Prigogine, etc.) (Box 9)
  - Catalog sheets (Box 9)
  - Notes for course “Thermodynamics of Irreversible Processes” (Box 9)
  - Reprints (Box 9)
  - Note cards (Box 10)
  - Published materials (not reprints): journals, books, meeting programs, CITCE and IUPAC reports, etc. (Box 11)
  - Proposal for development of a CO2-H2O solid oxide electrolyte electrolysis system v. 1 Technical proposal 1/8/68 (Box 12)
  - Chemical Thermodynamics (Chem 551, 552 Winter Spring 1956) (Box 12)
  - Study of Electrolytic Dissociation of CO2-H2O Using a Solid Oxide Electrolyte – quarterly progress reports 1-3 (1965-66) and annual reports (1966-67) and NASA contractor report (Box 12)
  - CITCE and IUPAC materials (Box 12)
  - “Les Extrema de Tension Superficielle et l’Indifference des Systemes Capillaires” these par Paymond Defay, 1932 (Box 12)
  - R. Defay, Elements de Chimie Physique (Box 12)
  - Reports on “Polarographic Study of Corrosion Phenomena” Navy Dept., Office of Naval Research (Box 12)
  - International Union of Pure and Applied Chemistry – 58th Ex. Comm. Meeting Minutes (Box 12)
  - International Union of Pure and Applied Chemistry – 57th Ex. Comm. Meeting Minutes (Box 12)
  - Correspondence re “Polarographic Studies of Corrosion Phenomena” office of Naval Research Contract # N6-onr-218 T.O.I. Project #NR-051-141 (Box 12)
  - Department of Chemistry Equipment Inventory 1946 (Box 12)
  - University of Oregon Library (Box 12)
  - Lecture Committee of the University of Oregon (Box 12)
  - Structure, Dissipation and Time, Structure and Entropy by I. Prigogine (Box 12)
  - “On a General Evolution Criterion in Macroscopic Physics” by P. Glansdorff and I. Prigogine (Box 12)
  - “Structure, Dissipation and Life” by I. Prigogine (Box 12)
  - CITCE, 1953-1955 (Box 12)
  - “Cinetique des reactions d’electrodes et phenomenes de polarization” (Box 12)
  - “Strategic and Critical Minerals: A Guide for Oregon Prospectors” GMI Short Paper No. 8, 1942 (Box 12)
  - Reprints (Box 12)
  - Reprints, IUPAC, Correspondence (mostly 1960s) (Box 12)
  - Corrosion Technology V. 2, No. 5, May 1955 (Box 12)
  - Sigma Xi Nomination Blank (Oregon Chapter) (Box 12)
  - U. of Oregon: Proposed course changes and report of service, 1947-48 (Box 12)
  - Receipt for books and supplies ordered at the Co-Op, 1948 (Box 12)
  - U. of Oregon: 1948 Commencement Program, Report on Staff Evalution, 1948 (Box 12)
  - Photographs (equipment, persons) (Box 12)
  - Current papers, reprints sent, etc. (Box 12)
  - Jones, Grinnell (Box 12)
  - Jogarao (Box 12)
  - Reprints (Box 12)
  - Chemistry Exams (Box 12)
  - Grade Requirements and Graduate Work in Chemistry, University of Oregon (Box 12)
  - IUPAC, 1968 (Box 12)
  - Thesis F. C. Coleman (Box 12)
  - CITCE, 1968 (Box 12)
  - Misc. Papers, Correspondence, photos, article reprints, etc. (3 folders) (Box 12)
  - Lectures (Box 12)
  - Correspondence (Box 12)
  - Zurich manuscript (Box 12)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 12)
  - Correspondence (Box 12)
  - Miscellaneous (3 folders) (Box 12)
  - Sommerfields’ Atonebau (Box 13)
  - National Research Council Draft Manual, 1967 (Box 13)
  - Reprints, manuscripts, notes, correspondence (Box 13)
  - Many miscellaneous files (Box 13)
  - Reprints (Box 14)
  - Contents not listed (Box 15-36)